<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A fourme of prayer to be vsed in priuate houses euery mornyng and euenyng</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1570</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 15 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09926</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20188.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S486</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22496341</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22496341</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25581</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09926)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25581)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1755:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A fourme of prayer to be vsed in priuate houses euery mornyng and euenyng</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>R. Jugge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>ca. 1570]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: *⁴.</note>
                  <note>"The prayers are those usually found at the end of Sternhold and Hopkins (cf. 2442, etc.) but this frag. does not belong to any of the known eds."--STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayers.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:25581:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25581:1"/>
            <head>A Fourme of prayer to be vſed in priuate houſes euery Mornyng and Euenyng.</head>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lmyghtie GOD and moſte mercyfull father, we do not preſent our ſelues here before thy maieſtie, truſtyng in our owne merites or worthynes: but in thy manyfold mercies, which haſt promyſed to grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t our requeſtes in hearyng our prayers, which we ſhall make to thee in the name of thy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued ſonne Ieſus Chryſt our Lord, who hath alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vs to aſſemble our ſelues together in his name, with full aſſuraunce that he wyll not only be amongeſt vs: but alſo be our mediatour and aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate towardes thy maieſtie, that we may obteyne all thynges which ſhall ſeme expedient to thy bleſſed wyll, for our neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Therfore we beſech thee moſt mercifull father, to turne thy louyng countenaunce towardes vs, and impute not vnto vs our manyfolde ſynnes and offences, whereby we iuſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue thy wrath and ſharpe punyſhment: but rather receaue vs to thy mercy for Ieſus Chryſtes ſake, acceptyng his death &amp; paſſion as a iuſt recompence for all our offences, in whom only thou art pleaſed, and through whom thou canſt not be offended with vs. And ſeyng that of thy great mercies we haue quyetly paſſed this nyght, graunt (O heauenly father) that we may beſtowe this day wholly in thy ſeruyce, ſo that all our thoughtes, wordes, and deedes, may redounde to the glory of thy name, and good example to all men, who ſeyng
<pb facs="tcp:25581:2"/> our good workes, may gloryfye thee our heauenly father.</p>
               <p>And forſomuche as thou haſt of thy meere fauour and loue, not only created vs to thine owne ſimilitude and lykenes, but alſo haſte choſen vs to be heyres with thy deare ſonne Ieſus Chryſt, of that immortall kyngdome which thou haddeſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for vs before the begynnyng of the worlde: we beſeche thee to increaſe our fayth and knowledge, and to lyghten our hartes with thy holy ſpirite, that we may in the meane tyme lyue in godly conuerſation and integritie of lyfe, knowyng that Idolaters, aduouterers, couetous men, contentious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, dronkardes, gluttons, and ſuche lyke ſhall not inherite the kyngdome of God. And becauſe thou haſt commaunded vs to praye one for another, we do not only make requeſt (O Lorde) for our ſelues, and them that thou haſt alredye called to the true vnderſtandyng of thy heauenly wyll: but for all people and nations of the worlde, who as they knowe by thy wonderfull workes that thou art God ouer all: ſo they may be inſtructed by thy holy ſpirite, to beleue in thee theyr onlye ſauiour and redeemer. But foraſmuch as they can not beleue except they heare, nor can not heare but by preachyng, and none can preache except they be ſent: therfore (O Lord) rayſe vp faythfull diſtributours of thy miſteries, who ſettyng apart all worldly reſpectes, may both in theyr lyfe and doctrine on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſeeke thy glory. Contrarylye, confounde Sathan Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, with all hyerlynges, whom thou haſt alredy caſt of, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a reprobate ſence, that they maye not by ſectes, ſciſmes, herreſyes, and errours, diſquiet thy lyttle flocke. And becauſe (O Lord) we be fallen into the latter dayes and daungerous tymes, wherin ignoraunce hath gotten the vpper hande, and Sathan by his miniſters ſeeke by all meanes to quenche che lyght of the Goſpell: we beſech thee to maynteyne thy cauſe agaynſt thoſe rauenyng Wolues, and ſtrenthen all thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes whom they kepe in pryſon and in bondage. Let not thy long ſufferyng be an occaſion eyther to increaſe theyr ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny,
<pb facs="tcp:25581:2"/> or to diſcourage thy chyldren, neyther yet let our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and wickednes be a hynderaunce to thy mercies, but with ſpeede, O Lorde, conſider theſe great miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ryes. For thy people of Iſraell many tymes prouoked thyne anger by theyr ſynnes, and thou punyſhedſt them by thy iuſt iudgement, yet though theyr ſynnes were neuer ſo greuous, yf they once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned from theyr iniquitie, thou receiuedſt them to mercye: We therfore moſt wretched ſynners bewayle our manyfolde ſynnes, and earneſtly bewayle and repent vs for our former wickednes and vngodly behauyour towardes thee. And whereas we cannot of our ſelues purchaſe thy pardon: yet we humbly beſeche thee for Ieſus Chryſtes ſake, to ſhewe thy mercies vpon vs, and receaue vs agayne to thy fauour. Graunt vs deare father theſe our requeſtes, and all other thynges neceſſary for vs and the whole Church, accordyng to thy promyſe in Ieſus Chryſte our Lorde, in whoſe name we beſech thee, as he hath taught vs, ſaying: Our father which art in heauen. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ <hi>Euenyng Prayer.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord God, father euerlaſting, and full of pitie, we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and confeſſe that we be not worthy to lift vp our eyes to heauen, muche leſſe to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ourſelues before thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlye maieſtie, with confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that thou wylte heare our prayers and graunt our requeſtes, yf we conſider our owne deſeruynges. For our conſciences do accuſe vs, and
<pb facs="tcp:25581:3"/> our ſynnes witnes agaynſt vs, and we knowe that thou art an vpryght iudge, which doeſt not iuſtifie the ſinners &amp; wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men, but punyſheſt the faultes of all ſuch as tranſgreſſe thy commaundementes: yet moſt mercyfull father, ſynce it hath pleaſed thee to commaunde vs to call vpon thee in all our troubles and aduerſities, promyſyng euen then to helpe vs, when we feele our ſelues (as it were) ſwallowed vp of death and deſperation: we vtterly renounce all worldly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, and flee to thy ſoueraigne bountie, as our only ſtaye and refuge, beſechyng thee not to call to remembraunce our manyfolde ſinnes and wickednes whereby we continuallye prouoke thy wrath and indignation agaynſt vs, neyther our negligence and vnkyndenes, which haue neyther worthelye eſteemed, nor in our lyues ſufficiently expreſſed the ſweete comfort of thy Goſpell reueyled vnto vs: but rather to accept the obedience and death of thy ſonne Ieſus Chryſte, who by offryng vp his body once for all in ſacrafice, hath made a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient recompence for all our ſinnes. Haue mercy therefore vpon vs, O Lorde, and forgeue vs our offences, teach vs by thy holy ſpirite that we may ryghtly way them, and earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repent for the ſame, and ſo much the rather (O Lorde) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that the reprobate and ſuch as thou haſt forſaken, can not prayſe thee nor call vppon thy name, but the repentyng hart, the ſorowfull mynde, the conſcience oppreſt hungryng and thyrſtyng for thy grace, ſhall euer ſet foorth thy prayſe and glory. And albeit we be but wormes and duſt, yet thou art our creatour, and we be the worke of thy handes, yea, thou art our father, and we thy chyldren, thou art our ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearde, and we thy flocke, thou art the redeemer, and we thy people whom thou haſt bought, thou art our God, &amp; we thine inheritaunce: Correcte vs not therefore in thyne anger, O Lorde, neyther accordyng to our deſertes punyſhe vs, but mercifully chaſtyſe vs with a fatherly affection, that all the worlde may knowe, that at what tyme ſoeuer a ſynner doth
<pb facs="tcp:25581:3"/> repent hym of his ſynnes from the bottome of his hart, thou wylt put away from hym his wickednes out of thy remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce, as thou haſt promiſed by thy holy prophete.</p>
               <p>Fynally, foraſmuch as it hath pleaſed thee for to make the nyght for man to reſt in, as thou haſt ordeyned hym the daye to trauell: Graunt (O deare father) that we may ſo take our bodyly reſt, that our ſoules may continually watche for the tyme that our Lorde Ieſus Chryſt ſhall appeare for our dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraunce out of this mortall lyfe, and in the meane ſeaſon, that we (beyng not ouercome by any fantaſyes, dreames, or other temptations) may fully ſet our myndes vpon thee, loue thee, feare thee, and reſte in thee. Furthermore, that our ſlepe be not exceſſiue or ouermuch, after the vnſatiable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyres of our fleſhe, but only ſufficient to content our weake nature, that we may be better diſpoſed to lyue in godly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation, to the glory of thy holy name, and profyte of our brethren. Sobeit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ <hi>A Godly prayer to be ſayde at all tymes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Onor &amp; prayſe be geuen to thee O Lorde God almightie, moſt deare father of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, for all thy mercies and louing kynd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſhewed vnto vs, in that it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thy gracious goodnes freely and of thy owne accorde, to elect and choſe vs to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation before the beginning of the world, and euen lyke continuall thankes be geuen to thee for crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng vs after thyne owne Image, for redeemyng vs with the precious bloud of thy deare ſonne when we were vtterly loſt, for ſanctifying vs with thy holy ſpirite, in the relieuyng and ſuccouryng vs in all our needes &amp; neceſſities, for ſauyng vs from all daungers of body and ſoule, for comfortyng vs
<pb facs="tcp:25581:4"/> ſo fatherly in all our tribulations and perſecutions, for ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng ſo long, and geuyng vs ſo large a tyme of repentaunce. Theſe benefites (O moſt mercifull father) lyke as we know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to haue receiued them of thy only goodnes: euen ſo we beſeche thee for thy ſonne Ieſus Chriſtes ſake, that thou wilt graunt vs alwayes thy holy ſpirite, whereby we may conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually growe in thankefulnes towardes thee, to be led in all trueth, and comforted in all our aduerſities. O Lord ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then our fayth, kyndle it more in feruentnes and loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes thee and our neyghbours, for thy ſake ſuffer vs not (moſt deare father) to receiue thy worde any more in vayne: but graunt vs alwayes the aſſiſtaunce of thy grace and holye ſpirite, that in harte, worde, and deede, we may ſanctifie and do worſhippe to thy name, helpe to amplyfie and increaſe thy kyngdome, and whatſoeuer thou ſendeſte, we maye be hartely well content with thy good pleaſure and wyll. Let vs not lacke the thyng (O Father) without the whiche we can not ſerue thee: but bleſſe thou ſo al the workes of our handes that we may haue ſufficient, and not to be chargeable, but rather helpefull vnto others. Be mercyfull O Lorde to our offences, and ſeyng our debt is greate, whiche thou haſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geuen vs in Ieſus Chryſt, make vs to loue thee &amp; our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours ſo much the more. Be thou our Father, our Captaine and defendour in all temptations, holde thou vs by thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull hande, that we may be delyuered from all inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and ende our lyues in the ſanctyfying and honour of thy holy name, through Ieſus Chryſte our onlye Sauyour, Amen.</p>
               <p>Let thy myghtie hande and outſtretched arme, O Lorde, be ſtyll our defence, thy mercye and louyng kyndnes, in Ieſu Chryſt thy deare ſonne our ſaluation, thy true and holy word our inſtruction, thy grace and holy ſpirite our comfort and conſolation, vnto the ende, and in the ende. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:25581:4"/>
               <head>Another prayer to be ſayde at all tymes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Almyghtie, moſt mercifull father in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, we beſeche thee for thy ſonnes ſake our onlye Sauyour and redeemer Ieſus Chryſt, graunt vnto vs and all mankynd thy holy ſpirite, to leade, gouerne, &amp; kepe vs in thy wayes and commaundementes, for we be wretched ſynners, full of ſynne, deſeruyng no goodnes, and vnprofitable ſeruauntes, that can neyther thynke, ſaye, or do any thyng that is good without thy helpe, for all goodnes commeth of thee. Notwithſtanding Lorde we be thy creatures, wherfore we beſech thee to helpe ſuccour, and comfort vs in this vayle of miſery, and increaſe our fayth, ſo that in all our enterpryſes we neyther do nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire any thyng but that may be to thy honor and glory, and to the profyte and commoditie of our neyghbours, and that thy wyll maye bee alwayes our wyll, and that our wyll may be alwayes thy wyll, and that we in all our troubles &amp; aduerſities may alwayes require thy wyll to be done. And we beſeche thee geue vs grace mekelye to beare thy Croſſe with thee whenſoeuer it ſhall pleaſe thee to laye it vppon vs. Alſo we beſeche thee to take from vs and to mortifie in vs all maner of couetouſnes, laſciuiouſnes, vayneglory, euyll thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghtes, Idlenes, lying, ſwearyng, ſtealyng, and all maner vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trueth, and graunt vnto vs vertue, good thoughtes, and in all our demeanour trueth, and a meke ſpirite, accordyng to thy promyſe, at thy wyll and pleaſure. Moreouer, we beſeche thee to geue vs grace to amende this noughtie and ſinnefull lyuyng that we haue hytherto walked in, and neuer to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to the ſame agayne: but from henceforth to proceade, increaſe, and continue in vertue, ſo that we may alway here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ſerue thee in feare and loue, and alſo that we maye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of this moſt miſerable and wretched worlde, in the
<pb facs="tcp:25581:5"/> fayth of Chryſt, at thy wyll and pleaſure, to whom for thy moſt glorious creation, and vnto thy ſonne our only ſauiour and redeemer Ieſus Chryſt, for his moſt precious redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to the holy ghoſt, for his moſt comfortable conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, be honour, thankes, glory, and prayſe for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A thankes geuyng to God in the Mornyng, for our ſleepe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lmyghtie and moſt gentle God, we thanke thee for the ſweete ſleepe and comfortable reſt that thou haſt geuen vs this night paſt, and foraſmuche as thou haſt commaunded by thy holy worde, that no man ſhoulde be ydle, but all occupyed in vertuous exercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, euery man accordyng to his callyng: we moſt humbly beſeche thee, that thyne eyes maye attende vpon vs, dayly defende vs in perylles, ſuccour vs, cheryſhe, comfort, and gouerne all our counſelles, ſtudyes, &amp; labours, in ſuch wyſe, that we may ſo ſpende this day accordyng to thy moſt bleſſed wyll, without the hurtyng of our neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and that we may diligently and warely eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewe and auoyde all thynges that ſhould diſpleaſe thee, ſet thee alwayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes, lyue in thy feare, &amp; euer worke that, that may be founde acceptable before thy diuine maieſtie, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde.</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
